Constance Pierrepont Noyes Robertson Papers
Constance Pierrepont Noyes Robertson Papers
1837-1972
Robertson, Constance Noyes.
18.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American novelist and author of books about the Oneida Community. Granddaughter of Oneida Community founder John Humphrey Noyes. Collection contains correspondence (1931-1972); manuscript articles and novels; research notes and drafts of articles, novels, speeches, stories; and memorabilia, including clippings, photographs, and reviews of her books. Some of the material relates to the Oneida Community and John Humphrey Noyes. Correspondence includes single letters of Carl Carmer and Alexander Wilder.
149546
Biographical History
Constance Pierrepont Noyes Robertson (1897-1985) was an American author, related to the Noyes family who founded the Oneida Community in Oneida, New York.
Constance Robertson was born in Niagara Falls, Ontario on September 27, 1897, the daughter of Pierrepont Burt and Corrina Ackley Kinsey Noyes. She was brought up in New York State where her family has long been connected with the Oneida Community, founded by her grandfather, John Humphrey Noyes in 1847. She graduated from Dana Hall in Wellesley, Massachusetts,in 1916 and attended the University of Wisconsin for two years. In 1918 she married Miles Robertson. After living in Syndey, Australia, the couple spent a year in the Far East and then went to London. They returned to the United States in 1921.
Mrs. Robertson first sold one of her writings, based on an experience in China, in 1920. From 1925-1930 she was editor of a small privately printed magazine. In 1931, her novel Enchanted Avenue was published. Five Fatal Letters, published in 1937 and written under the pseudonym "Dana Scott," won the novel prize at the Bread Loaf Writers Conference. Her first historical novel, Seek No Further, appeared in 1938, followed by Salute to the Hero, 1942; Fire Bell in the Night, 1944; The Unterrified, 1946; and The Golden Circle, 1951. Six Weeks in March was published in 1952 and Go and Catch a Falling Star in 1957.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Constance Robertson Papers are divided into three sections: correspondence, writings and memorabilia.
Correspondence, 1936-1953, consists of a few miscellaneous personal letters arranged chronologically. The bulk of the correspondence, 1931-1957, relates to individual writings and is included in the writings group with the appropriate manuscript.
Writings, 1843-1951, 1931-1966, consists of manuscripts and a small number of published pieces by Mrs. Robertson. Relevant materials such as correspondence, research material and notes, publicity and book reviews are included with most titles. The correspondence, 1931-1957, consists largely of incoming letters relating to Mrs. Robertson's requests for bibliographical and other research aids, and comments on her books after publication. There is a large number of letters from Edna Jacobsen, head of the Manuscripts and Historical Section of the New York State Library and from the American Library Service. Other correspondents include book dealers, public and university libraries, historical associations, publishers and friends. The Fire Bell in the Night correspondence folder includes two letters, January 8 and 26, 1943, and a manuscript on the "Jerry Rescue" by W. Freeman Galpin. A letter, November 2, 1936, containing research suggestions from Carl Carmer is included in the Seek No Further correspondence folder. Research material for Seek No Further contains copies of the only two issues published of the Spiritual Moralist, June 13 and 25, 1842, edited by John Humphrey Noyes and George Cragin. Also included are two manuscripts, 1843, by John Humphrey Noyes; two manuscripts, 1851, by an unknown writer; a letter dated November 23, 1843 from Alexander Wilder about spiritualism and a letter from John Humphrey Noyes, January 15, 1837 about religion, marriage and personal affairs.
Memorabilia, 1926-1957, includes newspaper clippings about Mrs. Robertson, her father Pierrepont B. Noyes, local history and miscellaneous subjects. Photographs of Mrs. Robertson, a concert program and list of names are also included.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material is arranged alphabetically by type and then by title.
Related Material
For more information about the Oneida Community, see the
Oneida Community Papers
and the
P. Geoffrey Noyes Papers
.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Fiction; New York State; Women Authors; Radicalism; Religion and philosophy; Carmer, Carl, 1893-1976.; Noyes, John Humphrey, 1811-1886.; Robertson, Constance Noyes -- Archives.; Wilder, Alexander, 1823-1908.; Oneida Community -- Archival resources.; American literature -- 20th century.; Christian communities -- New York (State); Collective settlements -- United States.; Utopias in literature.; Women authors, American.; Women novelists, American.; New York (State) -- History -- Fiction.; Articles.; Book reviews.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Manuscripts for publication.; Photographs.; Speeches (documents); Authors.; Novelists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Constance Noyes Robertson Estate, 1968, 1972, 1987.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Miscellaneous, 1936-1953 (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Articles
    - "Most Women Live in Dream World," New York Sun and the Syracuse Post Standard, September 26, 1931; September 27, 1931 (Box 1)
    - "St. Albans Raid"
      - Correspondence, 1946-1952 (Box 1)
      - Research material and notes, holograph and typescript (Box 1)
    - "So Far As You Need Me", April 1947; draft A, typescript carbon revised; draft B, typescript carbon; printed material, Reader's Digest (Box 1)
    - "Straw For These Bricks", original typescript (Box 1)
    - "Where the Sun Shines Out", 1948; correspondence; draft A, original typescript, revised; draft B, typescript carbon (Box 1)
  - Books
    - Enchanted Avenue, 1931; book reviews, printed material (Box 1)
    - Fire Bell in the Night
      - Correspondence, 1941-1951; 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Research material and notes
        - Anti-slavery, holograph (Box 1)
        - Jerry Rescue / W. Freeman Galpin, holograph (Box 1)
        - Outline, holograph (Box 1)
        - Gerrit Smith, holograph (Box 1)
        - Syracuse, New York
          - Bibliography, holograph (Box 1)
          - Local color, holograph (Box 1)
          - Maps, manuscripts (Box 1)
          - People, holograph (Box 1)
          - Pictures, 1942-1944; printed material (Box 1)
        - Underground railroad, 1943-1944; holograph, printed material (Box 1)
      - First draft, original and carbon typescript
        - Chapter 1-8 (Box 1)
        - Chapter 9-19 (Box 2)
      - Condensation in Negro Digest, August 1944; printed material (Box 2)
      - Publicity, 1944 (Box 2)
      - Book reviews, 1944-1956; printed material (Box 2)
      - Book reviews analysis, original typescript (Box 2)
    - Five Fatal Letters
      - Correspondence, 1933-1938 (Box 2)
      - Fragment, holograph and typescript (Box 2)
      - Published in Syracuse Herald, May 22, 1938 (Box 2)
      - Book reviews, 1937-1938; printed material (Box 2)
    - Go and Catch a Falling Star
      - Correspondence, 1954-1958 (Box 2)
      - Research material and notes, outline, synopsis, holograph (Box 2)
      - Draft A, original and carbon typescript, revisions
        - Chapters I-VI (Box 2)
        - Chapters VII-XVI, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Draft B, Chapters I-XVIII, 1957; typescript carbon; 3 folders (Box 3)
      - Printer's copy, annotated, 1957; original typescript
        - Chapters I-V (Box 3)
        - Chapters VI-XVIII, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Published in The Sunday Bulletin, Philadelphia, February 9, 1958 (Box 4)
      - Publicity, 1957; printed material (Box 4)
      - Book reviews, 1957-1958; printed material (Box 4)
    - The Golden Circle
      - Correspondence, 1946-1954 (Box 4)
      - Research material and notes
        - Bibliography, holograph and typescript (Box 4)
        - Chronologies, holograph and typescript (Box 4)
        - Civil War, holograph, printed material (Box 5)
        - Draft, army, holograph (Box 5)
        - Holmes County, typescript (Box 5)
        - Maps, holograph (Box 5)
        - Morgan Escape, holograph and typescript (Box 5)
        - Morgan-Hines Raid, typescript (Box 5)
        - Outline, holograph (Box 5)
        - Vallandigham, Clement, typescript and holograph (Box 5)
        - Working notes, holograph and typescript (Box 5)
      - Draft A, original and carbon typescript
        - Chapter 1-18, 2 folders (Box 5)
        - Chapter 19-26 (Box 6)
      - Draft B, Chapters 1-23, original and carbon typescript, revised; 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Printer's copy, 1951; original typescript
        - Chapters 1-11 (Box 6)
        - Chapter 12-21 (Box 7)
      - Excerpts, original and carbon typescript (Box 7)
      - Condensation in Sunday Bulletin, Philadelphia, April 20, 1952 (Box 7)
      - Publicity
        - Printed material, 1951-1952 (Box 7)
        - TV program, 1951; typescript carbon (Box 7)
      - Book reviews, 1951-1952; printed material (Box 7)
    - Mystery Story
      - Research material and notes, 1928; holograph, printed material (Box 7)
      - Draft, 1932; original and carbon typescript (Box 7)
    - Perchance to Dream
      - Correspondence, 1930-1931 (Box 7)
    - Salute to the Hero
      - Correspondence, 1940-1943 (Box 7)
      - Research material and notes
        - Bibliography, 1937-1940; holograph (Box 7)
        - Bibliography, General Daniel E. Sickles, holograph and typescript (Box 8)
        - Gettysburg, holograph (Box 8)
        - Lincoln panel, holograph (Box 8)
        - New York State politics, holograph (Box 8)
        - General Daniel E. Sickles, 1903; holograph, printed material (Box 8)
        - South Carolina episode, 1938; holograph, printed material (Box 8)
        - Speech panel, holograph (Box 8)
        - Tammany Hall, holograph (Box 8)
        - Virginius panel, holograph (Box 8)
        - Washington, D.C., typescript (Box 8)
        - Washington, D.C., geography, holograph, printed material (Box 8)
        - Wikoff material, holograph (Box 8)
      - Draft A, original and carbon typescript, revised
        - Parts I and II, 2 folders (Box 8)
        - Part III (Box 9)
      - Draft B, Parts I, II, III, original and carbon typescript (Box 9)
      - Publicity, 1942; printed material (Box 9)
      - Book reviews, 1942; printed material (Box 9)
    - Saratoga
      - Correspondence, 1937-1941 (Box 10)
      - Research material and notes
        - Anecdotes and incidents, holograph (Box 10)
        - Civil War, holograph (Box 10)
        - Colloquialisms, holograph (Box 10)
        - Costumes, holograph, printed material (Box 10)
        - The Cure, holograph (Box 10)
        - Geography, holograph (Box 10)
        - Hotel data, holograph, printed material (Box 10)
        - Local color, holograph (Box 10)
        - Maps, manuscripts (Box 10)
        - Miscellaneous, holograph (Box 10)
        - Newspaper clippings, 1746-1899, 1938 (Box 10)
        - Occupations, holograph (Box 10)
        - Outline, holograph, typescript (Box 10)
        - Politics, holograph (Box 10)
        - The races, holograph (Box 10)
        - Social scene, holograph (Box 10)
        - Songs, holograph, typescript, mimeo (Box 10)
        - Story notes, holograph (Box 10)
        - Transportation and communication, holograph (Box 10)
        - Working material, holograph (Box 10)
    - Seek No Further
      - Corresondence, 1931-1947 (Box 10)
      - Research material and notes
        - Bibliographies, holograph, typescripts (Box 10)
        - Kiantone Valley, new motor power / John Murray Spear, holograph (Box 10)
        - Kiantone Valley, "The Kiantone Valley and the Association of Beneficents," author unknown; "Odd House at Georgetown," author unknown; "Socrates tries City Management" by William S. Bailey, typescripts, typescript copies of printed material (Box 10)
        - Plot material, holograph (Box 11)
        - Miscellaneous, 1837-1843 (Box 11)
          Spiritualism, correspondence, 1837-1843, John Humphrey Noyes, Alexander Wilder
          Holograph manuscripts by John Humphrey Noyes, 1843-1851
          Printed material, The Spiritual Moralist, ed. by John Humphrey Noyes and George Cragin, June 13, 25, 1842
        - Spiritualists, holograph, printed material (Box 11)
      - Draft A, Chapters I-XXV, original and carbon typescript, revised; 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Draft B, Chapters I-XXV, original and carbon typescript, revised; 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Book reviews, 1938; printed material (Box 11)
    - Shakers
      - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 12)
      - Research material and notes
        - Bibliography, holograph, tyepscript (Box 12)
        - Microfilm (Box 12)
        - Miscellaneous, holograph (Box 12)
        - Outline synopsis, holograph (Box 12)
    - Six Weeks in March
      - Correspondence, 1949-1953 (Box 12)
      - Research material and notes, working notes, holograph (Box 12)
      - First draft, original and carbon typescript (Box 12)
      - Publicity, printed material, photographs (Box 12)
      - Book reviews, 1952-1953; printed material (Box 12)
    - The Unterrified
      - Correspondence, 1943-1950 (Box 12)
      - Research material and notes
        - Albany, New York, holograph (Box 12)
        - John Andrews and General John A. Green, Jr., holograph, typescript (Box 12)
        - Bibliography, holograph, typescript (Box 12)
        - Bibliography, riots, holograph, typescript (Box 13)
        - Copperheads, holograph (Box 13)
        - New York City, local detail, holograph (Box 13)
        - New York Herald Tribune, notes, 1963; holograph (Box 13)
        - New York State railroads, typescript (Box 13)
        - Outline, holograph and typescript (Box 13)
        - Politics, holograph (Box 13)
        - Governor Horatio Seymour letters, holograph (Box 13)
        - Troy, New York
          - Local detail, map, holograph (Box 13)
          - Regiment, holograph (Box 13)
          - Riots, holograph (Box 13)
        - United States Army, holograph (Box 13)
        - United States politics, holograph (Box 13)
        - Working notes, holograph (Box 13)
      - Draft A, original and carbon typescript, revised
        - Chapters I-IX (Box 13)
        - Chapters X-XX, 2 folders (Box 14)
      - Printer's copy, Chapters 1-40, typescript carbon, revised; 4 folders (Box 14)
      - Publicity, 1946; printed material (Box 14)
      - Book reviews, 1946; printed material (Box 14)
  - Letters to the Editor
    - Miscellaneous, 1946 (Box 15)
  - Short Stories
    - "Address to Captain White Eyes", 1943; typescript carbon, correspondence (Box 15)
    - "The Diving Bell", original typescript (Box 15)
    - "The Honey House", typescript carbon (Box 15)
    - "I'll Never Get Old", 1954-1955; holograph notes; draft A, original typescript, revised; draft B, original typescript, revised, typescript carbon, revised; correspondence (Box 15)
    - "Ma and the Devil's Picture Books", original typescript, revised (Box 15)
    - "Major Barley Settles the Odds", original typescript (Box 15)
    - "The Novel Necromancer", original typescript (Box 15)
  - Speeches
    - The Albany (New York) Club, Jan. 8, 1947; typescript carbon, revised (Box 15)
    - American Legion, Nov. 22, 1952; original typescript, revised (Box 15)
    - Beta Sigma Phi, Nov. 18, 1952; original typescript, revised (Box 15)
    - CAC Women's Division, Cooperstown, New York, Nov. 15, 1949; original and carbon typescript, revised (Box 15)
    - CAC Women's Division, Cooperstown, New York, May 21, 1955; holograph and original typescript, revised (Box 15)
    - Canastota Lion's Club, 1965; original typescript, revised (Box 15)
    - Columbian Club, Oct. 1943; holograph and typescript, notes only (Box 15)
    - Friends of Reading, Syracuse, New York, Nov. 27, 1944; draft A, original typescript revised; draft B, original typescript, revised (Box 15)
    - Hamilton, New York Fortnightly Club, April 22, 1947; original typescript (Box 15)
    - re Aldous Huxley, holograph notes only (Box 15)
    - Kanateenah Club, holograph, typescript notes only (Box 15)
    - re Jessie Catherine Kinsley, 1954; original typescript, revised and holograph notes (Box 15)
    - Ladies of Rotary, April 9, 1957; original typescript and holograph notes (Box 15)
    - Librarians Meeting, Sept. 24, 1949; holograph notes only (Box 15)
    - Madison County Historical Society, 1936-1943; original and carbon typescript, revised (Box 15)
    - Mansion House, May 14, 1944; holograph and typescript notes only (Box 15)
    - New York Library System, 1963-1966; original and carbon typescript (Box 15)
    - Oneida County Historical Society, Dec. 2, 1946; typescript carbon, revised, printed material (Box 15)
    - Oneida County Historical Society, Oct. 15, 1952; holograph; draft A, original typescript, revised; draft B, original typescript revised (Box 16)
    - Oneidas Club, Nov. 4, 8, 21, 1946; holograph and typescript notes (Box 16)
    - Onondaga County Historical Association, April 14, 1944; draft A, original typescript, revised; draft B, typescript carbon (Box 16)
    - Onondaga County Historical Association, Oct. 12, 1951; original typescript (Box 16)
    - Plymouth Church Auxiliary, March, 1943; original typescript, revised (Box 16)
    - Progress Club, Oneida, New York, Dec. 5, 1943; holograph, typescript notes only (Box 16)
    - Progress Club, 20th Century Club, Oneida, New York [same speech], Oct. 4, 1945; Nov. 11, 1946; original typescript revised (Box 16)
    - Progress Club, Oct. 28, 1954; original and carbon typescript, revised (Box 16)
    - Rome (New York) Wednesday Morning Club, Dec. 6, 1944; typescript notes only (Box 16)
    - Rome (New York) Wednesday Morning Club, Oct. 8, 1958; original typescript (Box 16)
    - Rotary Club, March 27, 1953; Oct. 30, 1953; original typescript, typescript notes only (Box 16)
    - Schenectady Women's Club, Feb. 16, 1948; original typescript, incomplete (Box 16)
    - Sherrill Public Library, May 18, 1944; holograph and typescript, notes only (Box 16)
    - Syracuse Corinthian Club, June 8, 1954; Oct. 21, 1954; research material and holograph notes only; also Progress Club, Oneida (Box 16)
    - Zonta Club, Nov. 7, 1946; holograph and typescript notes only (Box 16)
    - Unidentified, holograph (Box 16)
    - List, holograph (Box 16)
  - Unidentified
    - Writings, research material and notes, printed material, correspondence (Box 16)
- Memorabilia
  - Articles
    - Case, Richard G. / "The Oneida Community Lives on in Spirit," Empire, Syracuse Herald-American, June 1970 (Box 16)
  - Newspaper Clippings
    - Constance Robertson, 1938-1937 (Box 16)
    - Pierrepont B. Noyes, 1944-1946 (Box 16)
    - Local history, 1881; 1950-1959 (Box 16)
    - Miscellaneous, 1926-1948 (Box 16)
  - Photographs, programs, lists, 1942-1955 (Box 16)